Next, we will look at some Linux software
tools we can use to troubleshoot a problem.
As we go through each of these, the key is
to learn when you would use each tool and
the syntax behind each tool.
Many of these tools are similar to ones you
would see in Windows.
First, we have a ping, which runs the same
as in Windows, where we are trying to get
to an IP address.
I will type, ping 10.1.10.1, and select the
Enter key on the keyboard.
We see that we can reach this destination,
which happens to be a gateway router.
After letting this run, I will select Ctrl+C
on the keyboard to end this command.
Next, I will run the ip addr command, which
shows the IP address for each network adapter
on this device.
Traceroute is similar to tracert in Windows
as it shows a complete path from a source
to a destination.
I will type, traceroute www.learnkey.com,
select the Enter key on the keyboard, and
we see the path of routers going from the
source to the destination.
Tracepath, which I will run next, shows the
actual addresses of each destination on the
path to a final destination.
The dig command is similar to the nslookup
command in Windows, as the dig command when
I run it here shows the location of the current
DNS server plus the addresses of the 13 root
domain servers around the world.
The host command actually performs DNS lookups.
For example, if I type, host google.com, and
select the Enter key on the keyboard, we see
the DNS servers for google.
The netstat command, just like the one in
Windows, shows open and listening ports on
a device.
For this, I do not need to run netstat with
any attributes.
I can just run netstat.
Lastly, the arp command does in Linux what
it does in Windows: Show addresses and their
accompanying MAC addresses.